<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A gloryous medytacyon of Ihesus crystes passyon</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1523</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 18 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04426</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14550</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119432</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854639</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854639</idno>
            <idno type="VID">20068</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04426)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 20068)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1313:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A gloryous medytacyon of Ihesus crystes passyon</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprynted by me Rychard Fakes dwellynge in Dura[m] Rent, or ells in Poules by the yearde at the sygne, of the. ABC,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[ca. 1523]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; place of publication and estimated publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: [A]-B.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Jesus Christ --  Passion --  Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>¶ A gloryous medytacyon Of Iheſus cryſtes paſſyon</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of a wounded Christ</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:2"/>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of several men</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of mother with book, child beside her</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> woman recluſe and ſolyta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry coueytyng to knowe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the nombres of the wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des of our lord Iheſu cryſt pra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yed often to god of hys ſpe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyal grace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he wolde vou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che ſaue to ſhewe to her the ſayde woundes And at the laſt our lord Ieſu cryſte ſpake to her and ſayd. Say euery day in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hole ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re .xv, pater noſters &amp; .xv. aues and at theye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ende thou ſhalt worſhyp euery wounde and fulfyl the nombre of the ſame And alſo our lorde ſayd euery man that ſayeth theſe
<pb facs="tcp:20068:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> pater noſter / and theſe aues and theſe oray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons folowynge euery day in the yere And as ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as he ſayth theſe orayſones he ſhall haue .xl. dayes of pardon. And he that re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>deth to ony other ꝑſone theſe preſent oray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhall haue Ioye and blyſſe that neuer ſhall fayle but euer laſte withouten ende And where ſoo euer theſe preſent orayſons be ſayd or where he be that ſayth theym. I am preſent as. I was whan ſaynt. Paule dyde praye / and. I ſhall kepe hym from all pery<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>les / and. I ſhall defende hym fro wyc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ked ſpyrytes what man or woman ſo euer it be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doth ſay euery daye theſe orayſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of my bytter paſſyon for hys owne medycyne.</p>
            <p>¶ An aungel came vnto a good holy man and badde hym that he ſholde ſhewe to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man and woman that ſhold lerne y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd orayſons and ſay them deuoutly euery day And thys holy ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> came into a monaſtery. of ſyſters and ſhewed theſe orayſons to the abbeſſe of the ſayd monaſtery and ſhe ſhew<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed yt to her ſyſters / and ſome of them ſayde theym with grete deuocyon / and ſome for / 
<pb facs="tcp:20068:3"/> they ſholde not treſpace but they ſholde be delyuered frome euerlaſtynge penury / and honger. And I ſhall gyue them of my blode that they ſhall neuer haue thyrſte. And I ſhall put before hym the ſygne of my vycto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryous paſſyon in defence &amp; ſubſydye ayenſt All his ennemyes. And before hys dethe I / ſhall come with my dere moder and. I ſhall take / &amp; lede his ſoule to euerlaſtynge blyſſe. And whan that. I haue it thyder brought. I ſhall gyue it a draught of the chalyce of my good hede. And though a man had lyen .xx. yeres in ſynne and he wolde ſay theſe oray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſones deuoutly. I wyll forgyue hym all hys ſynnes / and ſaue hym from all temptacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s and kepe his fyue wyttes / and defende hym from ſodayne dethe and euermore kepe hym and his ſoule from euerlaſtynge payne / and all the ſynnes / that he hath doone from hys chylde hode vnto this preſente daye / I wyll forgyue him / and by my grace he ſhall be bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter than he was before. And what ſoo euer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e / aſketh ryghtfully of me or of my moder
<pb facs="tcp:20068:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> he ſhall not be denyed and. I ſhall kepe hym perfyte agaynſt all deuylles. It pleaſeth ſo moche god mooſt of myght that it is graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to hym that ſayth theſe orayſons though he were in the eſtate of euerlaſtynge damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacyon our lorde Iheſu cryſte ſhall chaunge euerlaſtynge payne in to the puryfycacyon of purgatory And yf he were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt pay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne of purgatory our lorde chaungeth it in to the payne of this preſent worlde / and bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth his bliſſed ſoule in to the glori of heuen that neuer ſhall haue endynge vnto the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the creatour and redemptour of humay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne lygnage brynge vs all</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <l>¶ The noumber of the dropys all</l>
            <l>I wyll reherſe in generall.</l>
            <l>¶ Fyue .C. thouſand for to tell.</l>
            <l>And .xlviii. thouſand well.</l>
            <l>¶ Fyue .C. alſo grete and ſmalle.</l>
            <l>Here is the noumber of theym alle.</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:4"/>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of image of Christ's face on a cloth</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>The veronycle I honour in worſhyp of the</l>
            <l>That made it through his preuyte</l>
            <l>The clothe ſet ouer his face</l>
            <l>His mouthe / his noſe / his eyen twayne</l>
            <l>Shelde me lorde for that in my lyue</l>
            <l>I haue ſynned with my wyttes fyue</l>
            <l>Namely with mouthe of ſclaunderynge</l>
            <l>Of fals othes and backebytynge</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:4"/>
            <l>And makynge booſt with my tongue alſo</l>
            <l>Of grete ſynnes that I haue do</l>
            <l>Lorde of heuen forgyue them me</l>
            <l>Thrugh vertu of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fygure that I here ſe</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of pelican feeding its young with its blood</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>¶ The pelycan his blode dooth blede</l>
            <l>Ther wyth his byrdes for to fede</l>
            <l>It fygureth that god with his blode</l>
            <l>Vs fedde hangynge on the rode</l>
            <l>whan he vs brought out of helle</l>
            <l>In Ioye and blyſſe with hym to dwelle</l>
            <l>And be our fader and our fode</l>
            <l>And we his chyldren meke and good</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:5"/>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of the host</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>The pens alſo. that Iudas tolde.</l>
            <l>For the whiche our lorde was ſolde</l>
            <l>Lorde kepe me from treaſon and couetyſe.</l>
            <l>Therin to deye in no maner wyſe</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of lantern, axe, and mace</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>The lantren that they bare in the lyght</l>
            <l>whan Cryſt was taken in the nyght</l>
            <l>Lorde kepe me fro nyght ſynne</l>
            <l>That I neuer deye therin</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of weapons</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>The ſwerdes / and battes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they dyde bare</l>
            <l>Therwith Iheſu cryſte to fere</l>
            <l>From fendes lorde kepe thou me</l>
            <l>Of them aferde neuer to be</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of staff</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>with a ſtaffe thou had a ſtroke</l>
            <l>Therwith Iewes thy heed broke</l>
            <l>with good chere and mylde mode.</l>
            <l>All this thou ſuffred and ſtyll ſtode</l>
            <l>whan I myſſe do ony or ony me</l>
            <l>It be forgyuen for thy pyte</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:6"/>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of hands</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>¶ The handes lorde that rate thyn heere</l>
            <l>And the hande that ſmote the vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eers</l>
            <l>For that payne lorde be my ſocoure there</l>
            <l>That. I haue ſynned with pryde of here</l>
            <l>And oll other ſynnes alſo</l>
            <l>That. I with eeres haue herkened to</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of cloth hung on rod</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>¶ The clothe before thyn eyen two</l>
            <l>They bobbed the, they knytted ſo</l>
            <l>Lord kepe me fro vengaunce</l>
            <l>Of chyldhod and of ygnoraunce</l>
            <l>And of many ſynnes alſo</l>
            <l>That I ſe with myn eyn two</l>
            <l>And my noſe in ſmelles of ſweteneſſe</l>
            <l>By vanytes &amp; wantonneſſe</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of coat</figDesc>
               </figure>The Iewes alſo keſt lote</l>
            <l>On thy precioꝰ purple cote</l>
            <l>A grete dyſayte to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> alway</l>
            <l>whan ony with dyce playe</l>
            <l>Lorde be thou my helpinge</l>
            <l>yf. I haue vſed myſclothy<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g</l>
            <l>By vaynglory and vanite</l>
            <l>Gracyous lorde pardon me</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of flails</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:7"/>
            <l>with roddes grete thou were to daſſhed</l>
            <l>And with knotted whyppes all to laſſhed</l>
            <l>Socour me lorde of my grete ſynnes</l>
            <l>Of ſlouthe and of ydleneſſe gynnes</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of crown of thornes</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>¶ The crowne of thorne on thy heed faſt.</l>
            <l>Thy heere to torne / thy ſkynne all braſt.</l>
            <l>Lorde kepe me from payne of hell pytte</l>
            <l>Neuer to deſerue it by myſſpent wytte</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of pillar wrapped with rope</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>To the pyller lorde alſo</l>
            <l>with a rope men bounde the ſo</l>
            <l>Herde drawne and ſtrayned faſt</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>That ſynewes from the bones braſt</l>
            <l>Lord loſe me of bandes in dyſtreſſe</l>
            <l>Though I am vnkynde ayenſt kyndneſſe</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Christ carrying cross</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>Thou bare the croſſe vpon thy backe</l>
            <l>Out of Iheruſalem it ys no lacke</l>
            <l>Thy fete ſleppes as thou forthe yode</l>
            <l>were ſeen thrugh ſhedynge of thy blode</l>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:8"/>
            <l>Thou metteſt with womem of Bedleem</l>
            <l>Alſo with women of Iheruſalem</l>
            <l>All they wept for thy grete tourment</l>
            <l>To them thou ſayd apertiment</l>
            <l>Ne wepe ye not for my ſmerte</l>
            <l>But for your chyldren wepe ye at herte</l>
            <l>For they ſhal haue tourment and payne</l>
            <l>And hondred yere here after certayne</l>
            <l>The ſteppes of grace to vs ye pardon</l>
            <l>whan we go with deuocyon</l>
            <l>On pylgrymage with good mynde</l>
            <l>Of my ſynnes lorde thou me vnbynde</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of nails</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>¶ The nayles through fote &amp; hande alſo</l>
            <l>Lorde kepe me out ſynne and wo</l>
            <l>That I haue in all my lyfe done</l>
            <l>with handes handled &amp; fete myſſe gone</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of hammers</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>The hamers bothe ſtronge and grete</l>
            <l>That perced holes in handes and fete</l>
            <l>Lorde be my ſocour in al my lyfe</l>
            <l>And kepe me harmles frowerde or knyfe</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of jars</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>¶ The veſſell of eyſell and gall</l>
            <l>Lorde kepe me from ſynnes all</l>
            <l>That to the ſoule be no venym</l>
            <l>That I neuer be poyſoned therin</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of large hammer</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>¶ whan thou had grete thyrſt and nede</l>
            <l>They gaue the eyſell and gall on a rede</l>
            <l>Of that I haue waſted in glotonye</l>
            <l>Lorde forgyue me whan I dye</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of spear</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>Lorde the ſpere ſo ſharpe ygrounde</l>
            <l>That in thy herte made a wounde</l>
            <l>It quenchehe the ſynne y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I haue wrought</l>
            <l>And with my harte in ydelneſſe thought</l>
            <l>with my prydde and booſt therto</l>
            <l>And myn vnburumneſſe alſo</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of ladder</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>¶ The ladder that was reyſed hy</l>
            <l>From the croſſe to take thy body</l>
            <l>whan I am lorde in dedly ſynne</l>
            <l>Gyue me repentaunce &amp; ſhryfte to wynne.</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of tongs</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>The tonges that drewe the nayles out</l>
            <l>Of fete and handes withouten dout</l>
            <l>And loſed thy body from the tre</l>
            <l>Of my ſynnes lorde loſe thou me</l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of men spitting on Christ's face</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
            <l>¶ The Iewes that ſpytte lord in thy face</l>
            <l>All thou ſuffred &amp; gaue them grace</l>
            <l>That I haue offended or ony man me</l>
            <l>Forgyue it lorde for thy pyte</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Christ surrounded by items relevant to the passion</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:10"/>
            <l>¶ The croſſe behynde thy backe bone</l>
            <l>That thou ſuffred paſſyon vpon</l>
            <l>Lorde gyue me grace in my lyue</l>
            <l>Clene of my ſynnes me to ſhryue</l>
            <l>And therto veray repentaunce</l>
            <l>with ſpace to perfourme my penaunce</l>
            <l>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Christ's body in the tomb</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </l>
         </div>
         <div type="verse_meditation">
            <l>¶ The ſeyulere wherin thou were layde</l>
            <l>Thy blyſſed body all to brayde</l>
            <l>Lorde graunt me or that I deye</l>
            <l>Sorowe of herte with teeres of eye</l>
            <l>And clene remyſſyon for to haue</l>
            <l>Or I be buryed and layde in graue</l>
            <l>And heuen to haue at my laſte ende</l>
            <l>Ieſu cryſt vs thyder ſende</l>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Innocentiꝰ papa ſecu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dus co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceſſit cuiuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libet hanc orationem ſeque<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tem deuore dice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti quatuor milia dieru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Indulgentia ⸫</head>
            <l>AVe vulnꝰ lateris noſtri ſaluatoris.</l>
            <l>Ex quo fluxit flumi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s fo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> cruoris.</l>
            <l>Medicina miſeria eſto nunc doloris.</l>
            <l>Aue plaga lacetis la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge et fecunda.</l>
            <l>Laua multitudinis fordes et emunda.</l>
            <l>Ne ledat inferius tuos mors ſecunda.</l>
            <l>Sed in viſu numinis fiat mens <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ocunda.</l>
            <closer>Amen. Pater noſter. Aue maria. Credo in deum. &amp;c<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayers">
            <head>¶ Here foloweth the prayers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .v. woun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des of our lorde. Iheſu cryſte</head>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ Of the fyue woundes of our lorde.</head>
            <div type="prayer">
               <l>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of the five wounds of Christ</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </l>
               <l>Gracyous lorde for thy gret paſſyon</l>
               <l>Obſerue my prayers that I do repete</l>
               <l>And on my ſoule take compaſſyon</l>
               <l>At my deth for thy woundes grete</l>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:20068:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Of the ryght hande.</head>
               <l>¶ wel of mercy paſſynge all myſdede.</l>
               <l>Of mercy I pray that I may ſpede.</l>
               <l>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of angel holding image of right hand</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ wel of mercy</head>
               <l>Thy ryght hande lord of trouthe &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yte</l>
               <l>That was through ꝑced w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a rugged nayle.</l>
               <l>Be my ſocour in the extremyte</l>
               <l>Of dethe whan he ſhal me aſſayle</l>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:20068:12"/>
               <head>¶ To the lyfte hande.</head>
               <l>¶ wel of grace y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> be my gyude</l>
               <l>Nyght &amp; day on eche ſyne</l>
               <l>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of angel holding image of left hand</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ well of grace.</head>
               <l>¶ Thy lyfte hande of ryght and Iuſtyce</l>
               <l>Fallen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to the croſſe by grete vyolence</l>
               <l>Delyuer me of euery deedly vyce</l>
               <l>That I may come vnto thy preſence</l>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:20068:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Of the herte</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of pierced heart crowned</figDesc>
                     <l>well of lyfe that euer ſhall laſte</l>
                     <l>My herte in the make y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſtedfaſte</l>
                     <p>Pyte.</p>
                     <p>Loue</p>
                     <p>Charyte</p>
                     <p>Welle of lyfe.</p>
                  </figure>
               </p>
               <lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:20068:13"/>
                  <l>¶ Thy herte that alway had mynde</l>
                  <l>By pycefull loue and charite</l>
                  <l>with feruent fauour to mankynde</l>
                  <l>was launced with grete inyquyte</l>
                  <l>The tyrauntes fell without pyte</l>
                  <l>Openned thy ſyde blyſſed ſauyoure</l>
                  <l>Bothe blode and water therout gan poure</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The vertue of that precyous blode</l>
                  <l>In honger and thyrſt of mortall ſynne</l>
                  <l>Be euermore my helthfull fode</l>
                  <l>Ther by thy blyſſe for to wynne</l>
                  <l>No dampnable werke lete me begynne</l>
                  <l>And that my herte may ſo enclyne</l>
                  <l>The for to ſerue as one of thyne</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The water that there gan yſſue</l>
                  <l>Vpon the croſſe tre dyſtylynge</l>
                  <l>Kepe my harte in menynge true</l>
                  <l>And clenlyneſſe of all thynkynge</l>
                  <l>The vyle werkes done in my lyuynge</l>
                  <l>By vertue of that water clere</l>
                  <l>Be clenſed and neuer to appere</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:20068:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Of the ryght fote</head>
               <p>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of angel holding image of right foot</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ welle of pyte.</head>
               <l>The ryght fote with the wounde ſo wyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>whiche in this worlde was all bare</l>
               <l>Graunte me grace my ſelfe to guyde</l>
               <l>That in thy ſeruyce I may fare</l>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <pb facs="tcp:20068:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>¶ Of the lyfte fote</head>
               <l>¶ well of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> neuer ſhall fayle</l>
               <l>Kepe me fro ſyn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>es y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> me aſſayle</l>
               <l>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut of angel holding image of left foot</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </l>
            </div>
            <div type="prayer">
               <head>¶ welle of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte.</head>
               <l>¶ The wounde made in the lyfte fote</l>
               <l>with a ſturdy nayle to the croſſe ere</l>
               <l>Gracyouſly be my refuge and bote</l>
               <l>And comforte in aduerſyte.</l>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Amen</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>¶ To the gloryous vyrgyn Mary Quene of heuen and moder of mercy</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of person kneeling at throne of holy mother and child</figDesc>
                  <head>Sancta maria Ora pro nobis.</head>
                  <p>Dei Memento Mei:</p>
                  <p>mater</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <l>BLyſſed Mary moder vyrgynall</l>
            <l>Integrate mayde ſterre of the ſe</l>
            <l>Haue in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce at the day fynall.</l>
            <l>Of thy poore ſeruant now pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> to the</l>
            <l>Myrour w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſpot reed roſe of Ieryco</l>
            <l>Cloſe gardyn of grace / hope in dyſparage</l>
            <l>whan my ſoule the body parteth fro</l>
            <l>Socour it fro myn enmyes rage</l>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:15"/>
            <p>Of ſaynt George the noble knyght. Of whome no torment coude haue myght.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>woodcut of knight on horseback slaying beast</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>O</hi> Blyſſed martyr of god ſaint George to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> begyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> laude and glory aboue al other knyghtes by whoſe vertue a kynges doughter beynge in drede and dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger to be deuoured of on horryble dragon was gracy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ouſly preſerued &amp; ſaued with in any other I poore and myſerable ſynner the requyre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſtedfaſt herte &amp; feythfull mynde that it wyll / pleaſe the to be my defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der in this lyfe from all temptatyous and perſuacyons dyaboly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>calles / as of the worlde the fleſſhe and the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyll. And at the mooſt dredefull houre of my dethe I humble beſeche the by thy blyſſed in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terceſſions to be as aduocat and mediatour towarde the ſouerayne Iuge for me whan y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mooſt tedious &amp; dampnable dragons of hell ſhall be redy to take my pore ſoule &amp; englou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te it within theyr infernall belyes / to thende y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. I may be one of the nombre of the ſaued and choſen people of paradyce. To the why<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che we may come by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> meryte of thy glorioꝰ martyrdome. Amen.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:16"/>
            <head>¶ To the blyſſed martyr ſaynt Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baſtyan whoſe greuous paynes no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne tell can.</head>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of saint flanked by archers and pierced with many arrows</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>GLoryous martyr of god ſaynte. Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>baſtyan whiche had leuer to be gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly tourmented &amp; ſhotte to dethe than to worſhyppe and do ſacryfyce to the ydolles and fals goddes. I ſynfull creature beſeche the for the ſayd paſſyon to ayde and ſocoure me whan the falſe and curſed enmyes ſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth and caſteth at me arowes of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pnable temptacyons of ſynne to enforce me to do oblacyons and ſeruyces to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſenſual volup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuoſytes of my frayle body for to bry<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge me to the dethe eternall of hell from the whiche kepe vs al / he that was borne in an oxe ſtal. Amen. Amen. For charyte.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>¶ Inprynted by me Rychard Fakes Dwel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge in Dura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rent / or ells in Poules chyr<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che yearde at the ſygne / of the. A B C</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:17"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of Christ risen from tomb</figDesc>
                  <p>xps reſurge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s ex mor</p>
                  <p>tuis iam non moritur</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <trailer>Here endyth A glorious Medytacyon Of Ieſus Cryſtes Paſſyon</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:20068:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
